A Guide to the Civil War Papers of John S. Eyster, 12th Regiment Pennsylvania Reserve Corps 1860-1907
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Civil War Papers of John S. Eyster, 12th Regiment Pennsylvania Reserve Corps 1860-1907
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11455
26 items.
This collection, 26 items, 1860-1907, consists of chiefly military and pension records concerning Captain John S. Eyster (ca. 1827-?) of Franklin County, Pennsylvania, Company K, "McClure's Rifles," 12th Regiment Pennsylvania Reserve Corps Volunteers (41st Pennsylvania Regiment). Also present are a few items concerning Private Christian S. Eyster (1853-?) of Alexander Hoore's Company F, 3rd U. S. Cavalry (postwar); Private James McConnell, Company C, 126th Pennsylvania Infantry; and Colonel Henry O. Kent, 17th New Hampshire Infantry Volunteers. Documents including muster rolls, military orders (mostly issued by Colonel John H. Taggart and Major Peter Baldy of the 12th Regiment), accounts, leave requests, and commissions. The collection also contains postwar materials concerning printed invitations, pensions and miscellaneous items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift: Greg Ramos, Weston, Connecticut, December 12, 1998.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 26 items, 1860-1907, consists of chiefly military and pension records concerning Captain John S. Eyster (ca. 1827-?) of Franklin County, Pennsylvania, Company K, "McClure's Rifles," 12th Regiment Pennsylvania Reserve Corps Volunteers (41st Pennsylvania Regiment). Also present are a few items concerning Private Christian S. Eyster (1853-?) of Alexander Hoore's Company F, 3rd U. S. Cavalry (postwar); Private James McConnell, Company C, 126th Pennsylvania Infantry; and Colonel Henry O. Kent, 17th New Hampshire Infantry Volunteers. Documents including muster rolls, military orders (mostly issued by Colonel John H. Taggart and Major Peter Baldy of the 12th Regiment), accounts, leave requests, and commissions. The collection also contains postwar materials concerning printed invitations, pensions and miscellaneous items.
During Eyster's service (April 5, 1861 to August 23, 1862) the 12th Regiment was organized at Harrisonburg, Pennsylvania, and attached to the 3rd Brigade of McCall's Pennsylvania Reserves Division in the Army of the Potomac. It was on duty at Camp Curtin and Camp McCall (Pennsylvania) and Camp Tennally (Tennallytown, Maryland). The regiment participated in various campaigns in Virginia during 1861-62 including Dranesville (a January 10, 1862 letter describes Eyster as "a faithful and attentive officer" who played an active part in this engagement which occurred December 20, 1861) and the Seven Days. However, there are no other direct references to battle participation in this collection.¹
Most items pertain to John Eyster's Civil War service as captain of Company K, "McClure's Rifles," 12th Regiment Pennsylvania Reserve Corps Volunteers (41st Pennsylvania Regiment) and members of his family. Among these are: Eyster's commission as a first lieutenant (May 7, 1861) signed by Pennsylvania Governor Andrew Curtin (1817-1894); two muster rolls of the regiment (August 10, 1861); orders issued by Brigadier General George A. McCall (1802-1868) concerning camp sanitation and the reporting of any suspicious lights or signals (August 19 & 24, 1861) and Special Orders No. 39, in which to curb sickness among the troops General McCall forbids sutlers and civilians to sell food or drink in the encampment (August 24, 1861); an American Tract Society publication Orders of Generals [George] Washington [August 3, 1776] and [George B.] McClellan [September 6, 1861] regarding respecting the Sabbath (September 6, 1861); a September 1861 account of the pay, subsistence, forage and clothing of a servant, William H. Mong [an African-American?]; a detailed outline of the regiment's daily camp schedule (October 3, 1861); an August 20, 1862, invitation for officers of the Pennsylvania Reserve Corps to attend the presentation of a sword to Major General George G. Meade (1815-1872); and, a 1866, a printed invitation to veterans of Twelfth Regiment Pennsylvania Reserves to participate in a Fourth of July parade in Philadelphia.
Occasionally, there are postwar comments on the reverse of some items. A January 31, 1862 account of Company K's savings by Eyster bears on its reverse "You can see how little they had to eat, to save the union and flag"; a leave of absence request, January 10, 1862, for Eyster endorsed by Brigadier General Edward O. C. Ord (1818-1883) bears a brief genealogical note: "Associate Judge from 1823 to 1832 Jacob Eyster/Father of John E./Mother Mary Slagel Eyster."
Also of interest regarding the Eyster family is a ca. 1861 photograph, by E. Woodward of Lancaster, Pennsylvania, of a young man [John S. Eyster?] in a militia uniform and leaning against a bayoneted rifle; a 1874 military discharge certificate, Fort McPherson, Nebraska, for Private Christian S. Eyster (b. 1853), Alexander Hoore's Company F, 3rd U. S. Cavalry and identifying him as a Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, farmer; a 1907 bounty claim form filed by Eyster's widow; and a December 17, 1907 letter from the solicitor for the directors of the poor in Chambersburg to C. W. Eyster, concerning a deed sent to Eyster's sister Fannie; on the reverse: "Leslie this was your Grandfather sword/And you are [entitled] to 360 acres of land through Uncle Christ."
There are a few items apparently unrelated to the Eyster family including 1883 and 1887 pension records of James McConnell, Fort Worth, Texas, formerly a private in Company C, 126th Regiment Pennsylvania Volunteers, a 1860 love letter and poem to Miss Lide McConnell from an unidentified correspondent, and a 1892 U. S. Senate report on a private bill for Colonel Henry O. Kent, 17th New Hampshire Infantry Volunteers [later the 2nd New Hampshire Infantry], asking Congress to order the War Department officially to recognize his wartime rank of colonel.
¹Frederick H. Dyer, A Compendium of the War of the Rebellion(New York: Thomas Yoseloff, 1959), 3:1582-1583; Samuel P. Bates, History of the Pennsylvania Volunteers, 1861-5(Harrisburg: B. Singerly, State Printer, 1869), 1:876-883, 905.
Contents List
- Item September 17, 1860 (Box 1)
  Love letter and poem to Miss Lide McConnell from an unidentified correspondent
- Item May 7, 1861 (Box 1)
  Commission, John S. Eyster of Franklin County, as First Lieutenant of the McClure Rifles, 2nd Brigade, 15th Division, "Uniform Militia of the counties of Cumberland, Franklin and Perry," signed Pennsylvania Governor Andrew Curtin (1817- 1894)
- Item May 7, 1861 (Box 1)
  Commission, John S. Eyster of Franklin County, as First Lieutenant of the McClure Rifles, 2nd Brigade, 15th Division, "Uniform Militia of the counties of Cumberland, Franklin and Perry," signed Pennsylvania Governor Andrew Curtin (1817-1894)
- Item July 25, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel George A. ___, Camp Curtin (Pennsylvania), orders Captain Eyster as officer of the day to detail his company for special guard duty
- Item ante August 10, 1861 (Box 1)
  Muster roll (12th Regiment of Pennsylvania Reserve Corps), Captain Eyster (73 officers and men)
- Item August 10, 1861 (Box 1)
  Muster roll, 12th Regiment of Pennsylvania Reserve Corps, Captain Eyster and Colonel John H. Taggart, Harrisburg, Dauphin County, Pennsylvania, for three years' service (95 officers and men)
- Item August 19, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel John H. Taggart, Camp McCall, calls Captain Eyster's attention to three orders issued by Brigadier General George A. McCall (1802-1868) concerning camp sanitation and the reporting of any suspicious lights or signals
- Item August 23, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel Taggart, Camp McCall, Special Orders No. 39; to curb sickness among the troops in the brigade General McCall forbids sutlers and civilians to sell food or drink in the encampment
- Item August 24, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel Taggart, Camp Tennally (Tennallytown, Maryland), issues orders concerning camp sanitation and airing out tents
- Item September 6, 1861 (Box 1)
  American Tract Society, "Orders of Generals [George] Washington [August 3, 1776] and [George B.] McClellan [September 6, 1861]" regarding respecting the Sabbath
- Item September 20, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel Taggart, Camp Tennally, issues orders to Captain Eyster for company of men to work as Pioneers
- Item September 1861 (Box 1)
  Account of the pay, subsistence, forage and clothing of a servant, William H. Mong (an African-American?), paid by Paymaster H. D. Maxwell and signed by Captain Eyster
- Item October 3, 1861 (Box 1)
  Colonel Taggart, Camp Tennally, to Captain Eyster, outlining the Pennsylvania Reserve Corps' daily camp schedule in accordance with General McCall's Orders No. 37
- Item December 14, 1861 (Box 1)
  Major Peter Baldy, Headquarters, 3rd Brigade, McCall's Division, orders the officer of the guard to report to General McCall
- Item ca. 1861 (Box 1)
  Address label, Capt. Hazzard, 3rd Division, 5th Army Corps/Capt. Eyster, Chambersburg, Pennsylvania
- Item ca. 1861 (Box 1)
  Photograph, by E. Woodward of Lancaster, Pennsylvania, of a young man [John S. Eyster?] in a militia uniform and leaning against a bayoneted rifle
- Item January 10, 1862 (Box 1)
  Camp Pierpont, Captain Eyster's leave of absence request (ten days) approved by Colonel Taggart and Brigadier General Edward O. C. Ord (1818-1883), commander of the 3rd Brigade; genealogical information on the reverse of this: "Associate Judge from 1823 to 1832 Jacob Eyster/Father of John E./Mother Mary Slagel Eyster"
- Item January 31, 1862 (Box 1)
  Account of Company K's savings by Captain Eyster; a postwar note on the reverse: "you can see how little they had to eat, to save the union and flag"
- Item August 20, 1862 (Box 1)
  Headquarters Pennsylvania Reserves, Rappahannock Station, Virginia, an invitation for officers of the Pennsylvania Reserve Corps to attend the presentation of a sword to Major Gerneral George G. Meade (1815- 1872)
- Item June 20, 1866 (Box 1)
  Printed invitation, w/envelope, to veterans of Twelfth Regiment Pennsylvania Reserves to attend and participate in a Fourth of July parade in Philadelphia
- Item February 3, 1874 (Box 1)
  Military discharge certificate, w/envelope, Fort McPherson, Nebraska, for Private Christian S. Eyster (b. 1853), Alexander Hoore's Company F, 3rd U. S. Cavalry; identifies CSE as a Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, farmer
- Item September 17, 1883 (Box 1)
  Department of the Interior, Pension Office, encloses pension certificate for James McConnell, Fort Worth, Texas
- Item September 17, 1883 (Box 1)
  Department of the Interior, pension certificate for Private James McConnell, Company C, 126th Regiment Pennsylvania Volunteers effective May 21, 1863, four dollars a month, for a shell wound to left thigh
- Item ca. June 4, 1887 (Box 1)
  Pension voucher, James McConnell
- Item April 7, 1892 (Box 1)
  U. S. Senate Calendar No. 563/Report No. 524, a private bill for Colonel Henry O. Kent, 17th New Hampshire Infantry Volunteers [later the 2nd New Hampshire Infantry], asking Congress to order the War Department to recognize his wartime rank of colonel officially
- Item post May 4, 1907 (Box 1)
  "Claim for Bounty, Arrears of Pay, Etc." unsigned form filed by the widow of John S. Eyster, showing his military service from April 15, 1861 to August 23, 1862 and authorizing George Bancroft of Washington to act as her attorney
- Item December 17, 1907 (Box 1)
  C. A. Suesserott, Solicitor for Directors of the Poor, Chambersburg, Pennsylvania to C. W. Eyster, concerning a deed sent to Eyster's sister Fannie; on the reverse: "Leslie this was your Grandfather sword/And you are [entitled] to 360 acres of land through Uncle Christ"